[Music]
having now covered dijkstra's link state routing algorithm we're ready to dive down to
the second broad class of routing algorithms take a look the distributed bellman ford
algorithm and this is really just it's a beautiful algorithm it's the best example
i know of how simple local intuitive distributed calculations can be used to compute
the same result in this case least costs pass as a centralized algorithm i
think you're really going to like this the distance vector algorithm for computing least
cost paths is based on what's known as the bellman-ford equation shown here and
while the equation itself might look a little bit daunting it's really pretty intuitive
the bellman-ford equation expresses the notion that if i want a minimum cost from
source x to destination y then that path must have one of x's neighbors
say v as a first hop so i'll sum the cost of getting from
source x to neighbor v plus the cost of then getting from neighbor v
to destination y this is x's cost of getting to destination y through neighbor
v and then i'll take the minimum cost path over all neighbors v since
x's minimum cross pass must pass through one of its neighbors v that's it
that's the bellman ford equation well probably the best way to understand bellman ford
is to take a look at an
bellman ford is to take a look at an
example so let's do that in the context of the network which you'll recognize
we're going to look at a source node u
and a destination node
z and notice that u has three neighbors
v x and w and here's what the neighbors
know
neighbor v knows that it can reach
destination z
with a cost of five neighbor x knows
that
it can reach destination z with a cost
of three and neighbor w
knows that it can reach destination z
with a cost of three
so that's what the neighbors know the
neighbors are going to communicate
this information back to you what is
this going to mean for you
for this example the bellman ford
equation says that the minimum cost
path from u to z is going to be the
minimum of three quantities
the cost of getting from source u to
neighbor v plus the cost of getting from
neighbor v
to destination z the cost of getting
from u
to neighbor x plus the cost of getting
from x to z
and the cost of getting from u to w plus
the cost of getting from w to z
if you plug in the numbers here you'll
find the minimum cost to get from u to z
is via neighbor x and at a cost of 4.
well the bellman ford equation expresses
a relationship among the distance
vectors
in neighboring nodes but of course we
still need to compute these distance
vectors
but the way to do that is naturally
expressed by the
form the relationship between distance
vectors and neighboring nodes
function how we compute these distance
vectors is going to follow form
and here are the key ideas behind the
distance vector algorithm
from time to time each node is going to
send its own distance vector estimate to
its neighbors
and when a node x receives a new
distance vector estimate from one of its
neighbors
it's going to update its own distance
vector using the bellman ford equation
that is node x is going to say well for
each node
y in the network i'm going to compute my
distance
x to y to be the minimum across
all of my neighbors v the cost of
getting from me to v
and then v's cost of getting from itself
to y
the distributed bellman ford algorithm
has three steps and all nodes in the network are going to perform the
same three steps so if i'm a node the first step is i'm going
to wait i'm going to wait till either i receive a distance vector from
one of my directly attached neighbors or i'm going to wait for a local
link cost change two after i receive one of these events i'm going to
run the bellman ford calculation for all destinations in the network using the most
recently received distance vectors from my neighbors three if my own distance vector changes
as a result of the bellman ford calculations i'm going to send my new
distance vector to each of my neighbors and that's it then i'm going to
iterate again well this algorithm could hardly be simpler and believe it or not
and hopefully you'll believe it when we're done this distributed algorithm will result in
all nodes having iteratively computed a distance vector that will tell them the least
cost path to every other node in the network and the neighbor to route
to to start a packet along that minimum cost path to a given destination
and note that unlike the link state algorithm a node doesn't know the entire
path from source to destination but in the end it doesn't really need to
does it it just needs to know
need to does it it just needs to know
which neighbor to forward a packet to in order to reach a given destination
along the minimum cost path well the distance vector algorithm has some amazing properties
it's iterative and asynchronous each iteration is caused by either a local link cost
change or the receipt of a distance vector update message from a neighbor and
we've talked about this as if it's
and we've talked about this as if it's
synchronous that all nodes are exchanging distance vector in lock step but in fact
nodes can iterate asynchronously from each other and with very different iteration speeds will
still converge the algorithm is also distributed and it's self-stopping each node notifies its
neighbor only when its distance vector changes neighbors then notify their neighbors only if
necessary and if no change is sent or no notification is received then no
actions need to be taken well that's it for describing the distance vector algorithm
it's pretty simple algorithm isn't it just three steps waiting to receive the distance
vector from a neighbor performing a distance vector calculation and then if my own
distance my local distance vector has changed i'm going to send my local distance
vector to all of my immediately attached neighbors that's it let's now take a
look at bellman ford in action and let's start with a high-level view of
the overall structure of a computation here's a simple nine-node grid network that we
use as our example it's pretty symmetric except there's a missing link between cnf
and this link here from a to b has a
cost of 8 while all other links have a
cost of 1.
at t equals 0 all nodes have their
distance vector estimates to their
directly
connected neighbors only here you can
see the distance vector in node a
its dv entry for destination b has a
cost of 8 and its dv
entry for destination d is a cost of 1.
note that these are just estimates of
the least cost paths
even to direct neighbors since as we can
see here
there's a 3 path of cost 3 to get from a
to b
which will found to be cheaper than this
initial cost of 8
via the direct link between a and b so
at t equals 0 let's assume that
all nodes have initialized their
distance vectors after doing so
send their distance vectors to their
immediate neighbors
at t equals 1 all nodes receive distance
vectors from their neighbors
compute their local distance vector and
if any component of their distance
vectors changed
they'll send their new local distance
vector to their neighbors
at t equals 2 nodes receive distance
vectors from their neighbors
compute their local distance vector and
if any component of their distance
vectors changed again
they'll send their new local distance
vector to their neighbors
and so on and let me stress here that
we've described the iterative process
here as if
all nodes are operating in link step
it's easier to understand it that way
but in fact nodes can iterate at
different speeds and this will still
work
well the short animation here has shown
you a little bit about the overall
structure of the distributed bellman
ford calculations
but we still need to look at the local
computation that's at the heart
of the algorithm when we take the
individual distance vectors from our
neighbors
we run the bellman ford equation over
and compute our new
local distributed distance vector let's
take a look at this local computation
let's recall that at t equals 0 all
nodes have computed their local distance
vectors which you can see here
let's take a look at b's distance vector
b knows that it can get to a
directly with a cost of 8 to c directly
with a cost
of 1 and to e directly with a cost of 1.
this is b's initial distance vector the
distance vectors of a
c and e are also shown here after
computing the initial distance vectors
all nodes send their initial distance
vectors to their directly attached
neighbors
only and let's suppose that at t equals
b now receives these distance vectors
from its neighbors
and here are the bellman ford
calculations carried out by b
at t equals 1 following b's receipt of
the initial distance vectors from its
neighbors
a e and c remember that at each step
when the new distance vector is received
a node will recalculate its own local
distance vector
using this newly received information
let's take a look at a couple of b's
calculations
let's first look at how b calculates its
distance to a
b says well my distance to a is the
minimum of three things
my direct cost to a plus a's distance to
itself which is zero
my direct cost to c plus c is cost to a
or my direct cost to e and e's cost to a
that's the minimum of 8 infinity  which is 8
infinity which is 8
so there's no change here in b's distance vector with respect to a but
now let's take a look at b's new distance table entry for d recall
that at t equals 0 b had an infinite cost to get to d
now it recomputes that cost as follows b says well my cost to get
to d is going to be the minimum of three things my cost to
get from myself b to a plus
my cost to get from myself b to a plus
a's cost to get to d my cost to get from b to c
and c is cost to d my cost to get o c and c
is cost to d my cost to get
to e plus e's cost to d if you plug in the values that
becomes the minimum of 9 2 and infinity which is 2 and you can
see that b similarly recomputes new dv entries for destinations f and h as
well and so here's the new overall distance vector computed by b note that
compared with b's previous distance vector there are three new lower cost entries for
destinations d f and h this new distance vector then becomes b's current distance
vector now let's take a look at node c again at time t equals
1 and after c has received b's initial distance vector let's see how c
recomputes its own distance vector but before doing so let's step back and take
a look at the picture here and
take a look at the picture here and
think intuitively about what b is telling c by b sending its initial distance
vector well b is saying hey look i can reach a at a cost
of 8 and i can reach e at a at a cost of 8
and i can reach e at a
cost of 1. well b is c's neighbor and c knows if that b
can reach e with a cost of 1
that b can reach e with a cost of 1
and c knows that it can reach b with a cost of 1 then
c knows that it can reach e with a
then c knows that it can reach e with a
cost of 2 via b and this is precisely the bellman ford equation that's
the intuition behind bellman ford it's not clear well hit the rewind button and
listen to that explanation again and so here are c's calculations of its new
distance vector let's focus on c's dv entry to destination e here c's calculation
simple since it's only got one neighbor c says for me to get to
e i can get to b with a cost of one and b tells
me that if b can get to e with a cost of one so
my cost c is cost to get to e v b is one plus
one equals two well you're probably thinking it's getting a little tedious to go
through one example after another but you might wanna do a few calculations for
yourself just to test your understanding for example consider the scenario here where node
e is receiving distance vector tables from its neighbors b d h and f
what's the new distance vector computed by node e  which entries have changed
the bellman ford algorithm can be
thought of as diffusing information throughout the network to appreciate this notion of diffusion
let's take a look at node c
and ask ourselves the question what do
other nodes in the network
know about the state of node c say at t
equals zero
and when do they learn this information
at t
equals zero c hasn't communicated with
anybody so no other nodes
have information about node c at t
equals one
c's state at t equals zero has
propagated
over to b by the exchange of distance
vectors so at t equals one
c state at t equals zero can influence
the calculations
at b at t equals one at t
equals two information from node c at t
equals zero has propagated further
to nodes e and to nodes a and imagine
your node e
at t equals two you're seeing the first
influence of the state of node c at t
equals 0 now at t equals 2 two time
units later
this notion of information propagation
speed it's almost like looking at a star
at night the light you're seeing now was
emitted by that star many light years
ago
and so it is with information
propagation in a network
the cost that e is seeing at t equals
two regarding
c reflects c state at t equals zero
even though e is receiving this
information at t equals two
well continuing on at t equals three c
state at t equals zero can
influence distance vector computations
up to three hops away
that's at nodes d f and h and finally at  equals four
t equals four
c stayed at t equals zero can influence distance vector computations up to four
hops away in this case at nodes g and i as well and note
that it's taken four time steps the diameter of the network for information to
propagate from one edge of the network to the other so far we've only
looked at the initial distance vector calculation after some number of iterations the computational
process will have quiesce remember if there are no changes in a local distance
vector i'm not going to send out distance vector updates to my neighbors so
eventually when there are no local changes computed anymore the algorithm will have converged
there'll be no more distance vectors being exchanged now let's take a look at
what happens if there are link cost changes because our distance vector algorithm can
already accommodate that and the steps are the same a link cost change is
noted if i'm a local node i
change is noted if i'm a local node i
note that local change i recompute my local distance vector using the new local
link costs as well as the old
local link costs as well as the old
distance vectors that i have for my neighbors and if my local distance vector
is changed once again i just send it out to my local neighbors so
the algorithm is pretty much unchanged so let's now take a look at an
example of how link cost changes propagate using the network shown up here on
the right and let's take the point of view of node y who sees
the xy link cost change from four to one it goes down so at
t equals zero let's say y detects this link cost change updates its distance
vector to note that now it's got a new cost to x of 1
and sends its new distance vector to its neighbors at t1 z receives this
updated distance vector from y updates its own distance vector computing its new least
cost path to x as 2 and now since z's distance vector is changed
z sends its distance vector to its
neighbors x and y
at t 2 y receives z's updated distance
vector
recalculates its own distance vector and
in this case
y's least costs in its distance vector
don't change
and so y doesn't send anything back out
to z
or x the algorithm quieses and is done
so just after two iterations the
recomputation of the distance vector
here concludes
and we'll note that the network wide
recomputation of the distance vectors
happened pretty quickly for this link
cost change example
the exact amount of time needed was
related to the diameter of the network
as you might imagine
and that's as fast as it could happen
given our earlier starlight analogy
and there's a saying in networking that
good news travels fast
when a link weight goes down in bellman
ford all nodes recompute their final
distance vectors
relatively quickly but what happens if
link costs go
up in this example here the cost of the
link from
x to y now goes to 60 and you'll want to
think about what happens in this example
but basically this is what happens when
the link cost goes to 60 y says uh oh
i better start routing through z since z
has
advertised the path to me with a cost of
5 to x
giving me an overall cost of 6 y informs
z of its wise new cost to x
via a distance vector update well z then
says this update and says
golly if y's cost to x is 6
then my cost to x is now 7 through y
and forms y y says uh-oh
if z's cost is 7 to get to x then my
cost is going to be 8.
z then says well if y's cost to get to x
is 8 then mine is 9
and so on this is what's known as the
count to infinity problem
and think about what would have happened
if the link cost had changed to 6
million instead of just 60
well be a lot of iterations of course
there are workarounds to the count to
infinity problem
but i think the larger lesson here is
that as beautiful and elegant as
distributed algorithms are
their operations and their pathologies
can often be subtle
well let's wrap up our discussion of
routing algorithms with a comparison of
link state and distance vector
algorithms let's start off
with message complexity we saw earlier
that the message complexity to do link
state dissemination
is order n squared for the link state
algorithm
for distance vector we learned that it
takes the order the diameter of the
network potentially order n for
information to propagate
from one end of the network to the other
and we saw that at each step
a node may potentially need to
communicate with each of its neighbors
in terms of speed of convergence we saw
that link state is order
n squared computational algorithm order
n squared
communication algorithm and we saw that
there can be oscillations the case of
distance vector
we saw that convergence times again can
vary
and there can actually be routing loops
while the algorithm is converging
and lastly let's think about what can
happen in a link state or a distance
vector algorithm if a router
malfunctions
or is compromised well under link state
a router can advertise incorrect link
costs but each router computes its
own routing and forwarding tables so
failure is rather localized under link
state
under distance vector a router can
advertise an incorrect
path cost for example a router could say
hey
i've got a really low path cost to
everywhere in the internet
this is known as black holing since each
router's distance vector is used by
others errors can then propagate through
the network as additional routers
advertise their new distance vector
and this type of black hole routing
failures actually occurred in the
internet
when a small isp advertised hey i've got
a zero cost passed to a major
isp i think that isp was att
when this isp wasn't really connected to
that major isp
and hey what network can pass up a zero
path cost to a major
destination network and so many other
networks in the internet who wanted to
route traffic to at  sent their traffic to this small isp
t sent their traffic to this small isp
where it was blackholed now imagine you're at t and you're saying hey why
am i no longer receiving traffic from a good portion of the internet anymore
well the answer was that traffic's been
black holed in a small isp instead
due to a misconfigured router in that
isp
well that wraps up our discussion of
routing algorithms dijkstra's
centralized link state algorithm
the distributed bellman ford algorithm
in the next two sections we're going to
cover the embodiment
of these routing algorithms in internet
routing protocols
the open shortest path first ospf
routing protocol
and the bgp border gateway protocol  think you'll enjoy them